# Dr. rer. nat. Martin Bies

# Curriculum Vitae



RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau
Department of Mathematics
Gottlieb-Daimler-Straße 48 (Office 433)
67663 Kaiserslautern, Germany
December 15, 1987 (Merzig, Germany)
Single (Not Married)
+49 (0)631 205 2850
bies@mathematik.uni-kl.de
https://martinbies.github.io/

German
Native
English
Full Proficiency
French
Modest (CEFR Level B1)

#### **SUMMARY**

I hold a **PhD** in **Physics** (*Heidelberg Univ.*, 2018), specializing in **string theory** and **mathematics**. My research is inspired by **computational analysis** of **massless spectra in string vacua**, resulting in publications on **toric geometry**, **Freyd categories**, **Brill-Noether theory**, and **root bundles**. Proficient in *julia*, C++, and *python*, I excel in **open-source software development** (*git*) to advance **computational research**. My diverse expertise emphasizes my interdisciplinary commitment. With a history of **international collaborations**, full **English proficiency**, and extensive **teaching experience**, I showcase a versatile skill set.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

CURRENT, FROM 10/2022 (FT)

# Mathematics Dept., RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER *Research Associate*

I enhance the toric geometry capabilities and develop advanced algebraic geometry tools for string theory geometries within the OSCAR computer algebra system (oscar-system.org). Funded by the SFB-TRR 195 – Symbolic Tools in Mathematics and their Application, I added/modified 142,000+ lines of code.

09/202I - 08/2022 (FT)

Dept. of Phys. & Astron., University of Pennsylvania, USA *Simons Postdoctoral Fellow* 

Continuation of Simons Foundation project.

09/2020 - 08/202I (FT)

Dept. of Mathematics, University of Pennsylvania, USA Simons Postdoctoral Fellow

Work with M. Cvetič and R. Donagi on root bundles and the F-theory QSMs (funded by the Simons Foundation).

10/2019 - 09/2020 (FT)

Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, UK *Long Term Visitor* 

Continuation of Wiener-Anspach project initiated at PTM, Brussels.

10/2018 - 09/2019 (FT)

PTM, Université Libre de Bruxelles, BE

Postdoctoral Researcher

M/F-Theory: Engineering Of Super Conformal Field Theories (funded by the *Foundation Wiener-Anspach*).

02/2018 - 09/2018 (FT)

# ITP, Heidelberg University, GER

#### Research Associate

AI-tools meet jumps in vector-like spectra (preparation of *Cluster of Excellence EXC 2181 STRUCTURES*).

#### **EDUCATION**

03/2014 - 02/2018 PhD in Physics (Grade: Magna Cum Laude)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND (PHYSICS) & PROF. M. BARAKAT (MATHEMATICS)

Heidelberg University, GER

09/2012 - 02/2014 Master of Physics (Grade: 1.0)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

10/2010 - 06/2011 ERASMUS exchange student

Imperial College, London

10/2008 - 08/2012 **Bachelor of Physics (Grade: 1.1)** 

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

#### **SCHOLAR SHIPS**

01/2010 - 02/2018 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes

2014: Awarded PhD scholarship. 2010: Awarded Master scholarship.

#### CURRENT COLLABORATIONS

FROM 2022 FTheoryTools in OSCAR

Initiated with **A. P. Turner** (*University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Later joined by M. Zach (RPTU KL-LD, GER), Prof. Frühbis-Krüger (Univ. Oldenburg, GER).

Goal: In OSCAR, create computer tools for F-theory applications.

Key features: Crepant singularity resolution and database of existing constructions. Status: First paper expected by mid-2024, paving way for cutting-edge applications.

FROM 2021 Toric Geometry in OSCAR

 $Together \ with \ \textbf{L. Kastner} \ (Technische \ Universita et \ Berlin, GER) \ and \ support \ by \ the \ OSCAR \ team.$ 

Goal: Solid foundation of toric geometry in OSCAR and integration with Polymake.

Status: **S. Telen**'s (MPI-MiS Leipzig, GER) lecture used OSCAR's toric geometry: arxiv-2203.01690.

An overview over the available functionality has been given in publication #10 (Mar. 2023).

**G. Muratore**'s (Univ. de Lisboa, PRT) article arxiv-2309.03741 is based on our work.

A dedicated OSCAR book chapter will detail further updates, due in 2024.

FROM 2020 Applications of Root Bundles to F-theory Standard Models

Collaboration with **Prof. M. Cvetič** and **Prof. R. Donagi** (*University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Initially, contributions from **M. Liu** (back then, PhD student at *University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Continued work with **M. Ong** (PhD student at *University of Pennsylvania, USA*).

Goal: Explore creating a single Higgs field in F-theory standard models using root bundles.

Status: Resulted in 3 peer-reviewed papers (#1, 2, 3) and preprint #9 from Jul. 2023.

Preprint #8, summarizing this program, will feature in *StringMath2022 Proceedings* soon.

#### **SERVICES**

- FALL 2023 Expert at European Commission: Accessment of research proposals in Mathematics and Physics.
- SINCE 2021 10+ letters of recommendation.
  - 06/2018 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board *Heidelberg*.
  - 12/2017 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Ellwangen III.
  - 05/2017 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Training for admission board members successfully completed.
  - 11/2016 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Heidelberg.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

```
0000-0002-9609-1693
                  ORCID
   TOTAL PUBLICATIONS
PEER REVIEWED/ACCEPTED
ACCEPTED/UNDER REVIEW
                          I/I
              OUTREACH
           UNPUBLISHED
                          4 (Based on peer-reviewed works, only.)
       H-INDEX (SCOPUS)
              JOURNALS
                         Journal of High Energy Physics (5)
                          Journal of Algebra and Its Applications (1)
                          Physical Review D (1)
                          Marked with IW.
     IMPORTANT WORKS
```

#### Peer Reviewed Publications

- M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Brill-Noether-general Limit Root Bundles: Absence of vector-like Exotics in F-theory Standard Models, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2022, DOI: 10.1007/JHEPII(2022)004.
- **2IW** M. Bies, M. Cvetič, M. Liu, Statistics of Root Bundles Relevant for Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs, Physical Review D, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.104.L061903.
  - 3 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Liu, M. Ong, Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs, Journal of High Energy Physics, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP09(2021)076
- **4IW M. Bies**, S. Posur, *Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors*, Journal of Algebra and Its Applications, July. 2021, DOI: 10.1142/s0219498822501869.
- **5IW** M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, L. Ling, M. Liu, F. Ruehle, *Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Jan. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP01(2021)196.
  - 6 **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, *Algebraic Cycles and Local Anomalies in F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)100.
- 7IW M. Bies, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, Gauge Backgrounds and Zero-Mode Counting in F-theory, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)081.

### Preprints accepted for Publication

**8IW M. Bies**, *Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models*, Preprint, https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08144, Mar. 2023, accepted by *StringMath2022 Proceedings*.

### Preprints currently under Review

9 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, *Improved Statistics for F-theory Standard Models*, Preprint, https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02535, Jul. 2023, under review at *Communications in Mathematical Physics*.

#### Outreach

M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry in OSCAR*, ComputerAlgebraRundbrief72 (03/2023), 20-25, Mar. 2023, https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08110.

#### Unpublished Works

II **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, C. Pehle, T. Weigand, *Chow Groups, Deligne Cohomology and Massless Matter in F-theory*, Feb. 2014, https://arxiv.org/abs/1402.5144.

#### Thesis

- M. Bies, Cohomologies of Coherent Sheaves and Massless Spectra in F-theory, PhD thesis, Feb. 2018, Heidelberg University Library, DOI: 10.11588/HEIDOK.00024045.
- 13 **M. Bies**, Cohomologies of holomorphic line bundles in smooth and compact normal toric varieties, Master thesis, February 2014, Link to thesis on author's academic homepage.
- 14 **M. Bies**, Intersectin D6-brane models on  $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\sigma \times \Omega)$  and  $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2 \times \sigma \times \Omega)$  orientifolds, Bachelor thesis, August 2012, Link to thesis on author's academic homepage.

# TALKS, POSTERS, CONFERENCES

### Invited Talks (8)

- 07/2023 Third Annual Meeting 2023 of SFB-TRR 195 (Saarbruecken, GER)
  - Title: F-Theory: Exemplifying OSCAR's Pursuit for Multidisciplinary Excellence
- 05/2023 Oberseminar algebraische Geometrie (Saarbruecken, GER) Title: F-Theory and Singular Elliptic Fibrations
- 10/2020 Philadelphia, USA
  - Title: Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory
- 06/2020 Summer Series on String Phenomenology (Virtual)
  - Title: On Stratification Diagrams, Algorithmic Spectrum Estimates and Vector-Like Pairs in F-theory
- 12/2019 Philadelphia, USA
  - Title: From F-theory Standard Models to Freyd Categories and back
- 10/2018 Brussels, BE
  - Title: Counting Massless Matter in F-theory with CAP
- - Title: CAP, Machine Learning and String Theory
- 07/2014 Aachen, GER
  - Title: The Standard Model from String Theory

#### Other Talks at Conferences, Workshops etc. (14)

- 07/2023 StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU)
  - Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
- 07/2023 StringPheno 2023 (Daejeon, KR)

	Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
05/2023	Computeralgebra Tagung 2023 (Hannover, GER) Title: F-Theory Tools: String theory Applications of OCSAR
07/2022	String Math 2022 (Warsaw, PL) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
07/2022	String Pheno 2022 (Liverpool, UK) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
09/2021	Summer Series on String Phenomenology (virtual meeting) Title: Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs
12/2020	String Data 2020 (virtual conference) Title: Vector-like spectra in F-theory (joined with M. Liu)
08/2019	Gap Singular Meeting and School (Lambrecht, GER) Title: Monoidal Structures in Freyd Categories
05/2018	Seminar on <i>Holography and Large-N duality</i> (Heidelberg, GER) Title: <i>Conformal Invariants; Fefferman–Graham Expansion; Graham–Lee Theorem</i> (with M. Zikidis)
07/2017	String Pheno 2017 (Virginia, USA) Title: Zero Mode Counting in F-Theory via CAP
08/2014	GAP Days (Aachen, GER) Title: String Theory, Sheaf Cohomology and the homalg Package
05/2014	Seminar Series What is? (Heidelberg, GER) Title: What is a Fermion/Boson (in Quantum Mechanics)?
02/2014	Heidelberg, GER Title: Cohomology of Holomorphic Pullback Line Bundles on Smooth, Compact Normal Toric Varieties
05/2012	Heidelberg, GER Title: Intersecting D6-Brane Models
Posters at (	Conferences, Workshops etc. (2)
07/2023	StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU) Title: FTheoryTools – A Computer Tool for Singular Elliptic Fibrations
09/2019	Strings and Geometry (Oxford, UK) Title: Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors
Conference.	s attended without Talk or Poster Contribution (18)
07/2022	Strings 2022 (Vienna, AT)
06/2022	Simons Collab.: Geometry, Topology and Singular Special Holonomy Spaces (Freiburg, GER)
11/2021	Simons Collab. (Homological Mirror Symmetry) Annual Meeting (New York, USA)
09/2021	Simons Collab.: Progress and Open Problems (Stony Brook, USA)
09/2021	Simons Collab. (Special Holonomy in Geometry, Analysis, Phys.) Annual Meeting (New York, USA
07/2021	String Pheno 2021 (virtual conference)
06/2021	Strings 2021 (virtual conference)
06/2021	String Math 2021 (virtual conference)
06/2020	String Pheno 2020 (virtual conference)

```
Strings 2019 (Brussels, BE)
07/2019
03/2018
         String Data 2018 (Munich, GER)
         String Math 2015 (Sanya, CN)
12/2015
         Third GAP Days (Trondheim, NO)
09/2015
         Second GAP Days (Aachen, GER)
03/2015
         Physics and Geometry of F-Theory (Munich, GER)
02/2015
         Homological Perturbation Theory (Galway, IE)
12/2014
02/2014
         Geometry and Physics of String Compactifications (Heidelberg, GER)
```

### TEACHING RECORD

Autonomous Instruction of Lecture Courses at the University Of Pennsylvania, USA

Period	Title	Students	Weekly Teaching	Evaluation
01/2022 - 05/2022	Computational Linear Algebra	29	$2 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$	2.12
01/2021 - 05/2021	Computational Linear Algebra	57	$2 \times 1.5  \mathrm{hours}$	2.04

Scale: Poor (o), Fair (1), Good (2), Very good (3), Excellent (4).

### Senior Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching
10/2023 – current	Algebraic Geometry	RPTU KL-LD, GER	6	$1 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$
04/2018 - 10/2018	Methods of Math. Phys.	Heidelberg University, GER	51	$1 \times 1.5  \text{hours}$
04/2016 - 09/2016	General Relativity	Heidelberg University, GER	132	$1 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$

## Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Weekly Teaching
10/2016 - 03/2017	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5  \text{hours}$
04/2015 - 09/2015	Theoretical Physics IV	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
10/2014 - 03/2015	Quantum Field Theory	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
10/2013 - 03/2014	Theoretical Physics III	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
04/2013 - 09/2013	Theoretical Physics II	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5$ hours
10/2012 - 03/2013	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$